IU Oral History Archive 1991-1998
Indiana University Libraries
- Eissler, Donald November 9, 1993, 91-215; 26 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 66 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Donald Eissler, born on October 12, 1930, is a 1952 graduate of Indiana University and veteran of the Korean War. In this interview, he discusses his memories of the university and the growth and changes the university has experienced. A former student body president, Eissler relates anecdotes about campus politics, Greek life, athletics, and various figure who exerted significant influences on his life, including Herman B Wells, Christian Jung, and Gretchen Kemp. In addition, he praises Indiana University's School of Music, especially because of the education it afforded his son, David Eissler, a successful singer. Eissler also discusses problems and positive aspects of Indiana University through time, and he speaks of the university's administration.
  Indiana University School of Music
  Bell, Joshua; Bernstein, Leonard; Cohen, Jere Michael; Eissler, David; Jung, Christian; Kemp, Gretchen; Powell, Bill; Shoemaker, Raymond L.; Wells, Herman B
  campus politics; drugs; fraternities; Indiana University administration; Indiana University athletics; Korean War; music; sororities
- Elliott, Byron Kauffman June 1, 1992, 91-107; 14 pages; 1 cassette, 1 7/8 ips, 54 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Byron K. Elliott was born in Indianapolis in 1899. He attended Shortridge High School there and then went to Bloomington to attend Indiana University. He went to law school at Harvard University, then returned to Indiana, where he was chief deputy prosecutor in Marion County before he was elected to the Indiana Superior. Elliott then went on to work for the American Life Convention, a life insurance association, and then went to the John Hancock Life Insurance Company. Elliott also describes his work with the Indiana University Foundation and reflects on the changes in the university since his student days from 1917 to 1920.
  American Life Convention; Harvard Law School; Indiana University Foundation; John Hancock Company; Ku Klux Klan
  attorney; Indiana business; judge
  Bryan, William Lowe; Oberholtz, Madge; Remy, William H.; Stephenson, David Curtis
  Bloomington, Indiana; Marion County, Indiana
  1918 Influenza Epidemic; student life; World War I
- Elliott, PeggySeptember 12, 1994, 91-281; 10 pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 30 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Peggy Elliott, born in Matewon, West Virginia on May 27, 1937, was both a student and faculty member at Indiana University. She discusses her time as a female student with children in the 1970s, her work as an administrator at Indiana University Northwest, and the challenges of being a female chancellor. Also she discusses changes to Indiana University Northwest under her leadership and Indiana University Northwest's relationship to the Indiana University system.
  American Council on Education; Indiana University Northwest; IUPUI; Northwestern University; Transylvania University
  Gary, Indiana; Matewon, West Virginia
  administartor; chancellor; professor; teacher
  Brown, Sylvia; Orescanin, Dan
  female faculty; female students; women faculty; women in academia; women students
- Fay, Leo June 7, 1994, 91-268; 26 pages; 2 audiocassettes, 83 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Leo Fay arrived at Indiana University in 1952 as a professor in the School of Education. He discusses his experiences setting up educational systems in Thailand on behalf of the university. He also talks about his university career, his service on the faculty council, the changes that have taken place in education since the nineteen fifties, Indiana University's different presidents, and the qualities that make a good university.
  Army Air Corps; Concordia University-St. Paul; ERIC; Reader's Digest; School of Public and Environmental Affairs; University of Minnesota
  education professor; faculty council secretary
  Confucius; Ryan, John W.; Wells, Herman B; Wright, Wendell W. "Whack"
  Thailand
  campus presidents; censorship; conservatism; elementary education; libraries; McCarthyism; reading; teaching; teaching awards; World War II
- Ferrell, Robert February 13, 1998, 96-40; 43 pages; 3 cassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 2 hours, 50 minutes; index; Sheehan, Steven
  Access Statis
  Robert H. Ferrell discusses his tenure as a professor at the Indiana University Department of History. He describes how his experiences as a soldier in World War II made him interested in studying history. He talks about his graduate experience at Yale and his mentor, Samuel Bemis. He describes the writing of his dissertation, and other publications after that. He talks about people he knows in the history department, and contacts with other historians in the United States. He describes the importance of being a good teacher as well as a good scholar, which he feels are inseparable despite the push in universities today where scholarship and publishing are valued far above teaching skills. He speaks of the declining quality of students since the 1960s. Finally, he speaks of the reasons for his retirement.
  Bowling Green University; Yale University
  pianist
  Bemis, Samuel Flagg; Benns, Lee; Bryan, William Lowe; Buley, Roscoe Carlyle; Byrd, Cecil; Byrnes, Robert F.; Castle, William R., Jr.; Curtis, Lewis; Dulles, Foster Rhea; Ehrlich, Thomas; Friedman, Larry; Grant, James; Grossberg, Michael; Gucker, Frank Thomson; Jameson, J. Franklin; Kaplan, Larry; Kohlmeier, Albert Ludwig; Kunz, Diane; Lowengrub, Mort; O’Neil, Bob; Ryan, John W.; Stark, Lloyd; Truman, President Harry; Wells, Herman B.; Winther, Oscar Osburn
  American history studies; Foreign Relations of the United States; Indiana University hiring practices; publishing; study habits; teaching; World War II; writing styles
- Finkel, Carol Lee Drevno March 8, 1994, 91-241; 22 pages; 2 cassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour, 21 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Carol Lee Finkel, née Drevno, was born in Chicago in 1926. She lived there and in Providence, Rhode Island, before coming to Indiana University in 1944. She describes her student days at Indiana University including her School of Music recitals, memorable classes and instructors, and post-World War II changes on campus. After her 1948 graduation, Finkel continued her involvement with the university through alumni association activities and the education of her four children. She describes her post-graduation career as a musician and owner of a wholesale automotive distribution business.
  Indiana State Music Association; Indiana University Alumni Association; Indiana University School of Music
  Finkel
  musician; pianist
  Collins, Ralph; Bain, Wilfred C.; Ehrlich, Thomas; Knight, Bob; Ryan, John W.; Wells, Herman B
  Bloomington, Indiana; Shelbyville, Indiana
  mail order business; musical recitals; race relations; student unrest; World War II
- Fisk, Milton T. February 28, 1997, 96-035; Not transcribed; 3 cassettes, 1 7/8 ips; 2 hours, 50 minutes; no index; Kraemer, Peter
  Milton Fisk, born February 15, 1932, discusses his early life and education. He discusses becoming interested in philosophy, studying abroad, teaching it, and how its concepts have changed. He talks about comming to Indiana University (IU) and his first impressions and how its changed. He speaks of his involvement in radical politics including the faculty union and collective bargaining at IU.
  Indiana University Department of Philosophy; Notre Dame; Yale
  philosophy professor
  faculty union; Indiana University changes; Indiana University presidents; radical politics; religion; teaching
- Fletchall, Eugene D. October 23, 1991, 91-080; 15 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 50 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Eugene D. Fletchall, born on August 19, 1908, attended Indiana University as an undergraduate from 1926 to 1929 and returned a few years later to complete both his undergraduate degree and his law degree, which he earned in 1934. A distinguished alumnus, Fletchall recalls his days as a student at Indiana University with respect to student life, Greek life, the Great Depression, and athletics. In addition, he describes his relations with and anecdotes about influential figures at Indiana University, including William Lowe Bryan, Ward G. Biddle, Herman B Wells, and Hoagy Carmichael. Fletchall also discusses his participation in Phi Gamma Delta, the student union board, and later in life, the Indiana University alumni association.
  Indiana University Alumni Association; Indiana University student union board; Phi Gamma Delta
  Biddle, Ward G.; Bryan, William Lowe; Carmichael, Hoagy; McMillin, Alvin N. "Bo"; Nelson, Alice; Rich, Claude T.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Willis, Hugh
  fraternities; Great Depression; Indiana University athletics; student life
- Flock, Kurt Lee July 16, 1992, 91-125; 15 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 40 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on August 20, 1953, Kurt Flock is a 1977 Indiana University alumnus and former student body president who discusses his student experiences in this interview. He recalls aspects of campus politics and the impact of the Vietnam War on the university. In addition, Flock cites examples of controversy on campus including co-educational housing. Flock was also extensively involved in the Indiana Student Association and was actively involved with the Indiana Daily Student. A professional in the area of real estate, Flock gives the credit for his successful career to the broad-based education he received at Indiana University.
  Indiana Daily Student; Indiana University Student Association
  real estate agent
  Danzig, Steve
  campus politics; co-educational housing; Vietnam War
- Forbes, J. Thomas June 16, 1992, 91-109; 31 pages; 2 audiocassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 87 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Thomas Forbes in an Indiana native who received his BA from Indiana University in the nineteen eighties. He served as the student body president and discusses the work he did in this capacity and the changes that he witnessed during the Ehrlich administration. He spends the bulk of his interview discussing cultural diversity, the Center on Philanthropy, and the different campuses of Indiana University.
  Center on Philanthropy; IUPUI; Middle Way House; MTV; School of Public and Environmental Affairs; Women's Wheels
  student body president
  Baker, David; Elliot, Peggy; Hershey, Marjorie; Moody, Michael; Stein, Stephen; Wiggins, William; Wise, Larry
  campus safety; diversity; Indiana University regional campuses; multiculturalism; philanthropy; student government; student protests; television; university finances; volunteerism
- Frick, David Rhoads July 20, 1992, 91-128; 13 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 37 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1944, David R. Frick is a 1966 Indiana University alumnus and former student body president who discusses some of his student experiences in this interview. He speaks of the effects of the Vietnam War on campus and the repercussions of events such as the John F. Kennedy assassination. In addition, he talks of campus politics in the nineteen sixties and his involvement as the student body president. A successful attorney, Frick continued his involvement with Indiana University through continuing participation in the alumni association.
  attorney
  Heineman, Charles; Kessler, James B.; Lofton, Guy; Stahr, Elvis J.; Wells, Herman B
  campus politics; John F. Kennedy assassination; Vietnam War
- Gaber, GeorgeOctober 31, 1996, 96-028; 36 pp.; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 118 minutes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Born on February 24, 1916 in New York, New York, Gaber accepted a position as music professor with the university I 1960. Gaber discusses his education and experience as the son of immigrants growing up in the Lower East Side. He discusses his time at Juilliard Conservatory, his experiences in his early career as a percussionist, and his transition to professor in 1960. He also discusses his development of the percussion curriculum in the music school. Finally, he gives details about his experience retiring from the university and what he has done post-retirement.
  American Broadcasting Company; Hofstra University; Juilliard Conservatory; New School for Social Research; Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra
  Bukovina, Austria; New York, New York
  music professor; musician
  Bain, Wilfred; Bennett, Robert Russell; Bernstein, Leonard; Ellington, Duke; Horney, Karen
  curriculum; immigrants; jazz; student diversity; teaching methods
- Gambill, Christopher Brett July 17, 1992, 91-126; 24 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 72 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Christopher Gambill, born on September 30, 1957, is a 1979 Indiana University alumnus and 1983 graduate of the Indiana University School of Law. In this interview, he speaks extensively about his days as a student. He discusses residence halls, Greek life, campus life, campus politics, and campus controversy. Two examples of controversy on the Indiana University campus included the heated contention surrounding draft registration and the bringing of Jane Fonda to campus to speak about economic democracy. As a former student body president and married student, Gambill presents a unique perspective and experience regarding the previously mentioned issues and the administration of Indiana University. The interview includes excerpts describing Gambill's association with many important people, such as Jimmy Carter, Jane Fonda, and Gwendolyn Carter.
  Indiana University School of Law
  Carter, Gwendolyn; Carter, James Earl, Jr.; Fonda, Jane; Knight, Bob; Mayberry, Phil
  campus politics; campus protests; draft registration; fraternities; Hilltop Gardens; Indiana University administration; sororities; student housing; student life
- Garrison, Paul C. May 9, 1994, 91-252; 9 pages; 1 audiocassette, 17 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Paul Garrison received his masters in education from Indiana University in the nineteen thirties. He remained with Indiana University as a professor and served as president of both the Alumni Association and the School of Education Alumni Association. He also discusses the changes that have taken place at Indiana University since the nineteen thirties.
  teacher
  Franzen, Carl; McMillin, Alvin N. "Bo"; Wells, Herman B; Wright, Wendell W. "Whack"
  water shortages
- Gates, Robert June 14, 1991, 91-068; 14 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 39 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Robert Gates attended Indiana University as an undergraduate from 1938 to 1942 and then received his law degree in 1949. He began practicing law but remained involved with university life, serving as a trustee for twenty-one years and as president of the Union Board. Gates discusses the challenges of funding and maintaining state schools, the development of programs, and the impact that the nineteen sixties had on Indiana University's campus.
  Indiana University School of Medicine; Sigma Alpha Epsilon
  attorney; Indiana University trustee; navy paymaster; Union Board president
  Ryan, John W.; Wells, Herman B
  campus buildings; campus growth; endowments; Indiana University Memorial Union; nineteen sixties; optometry; tuition; university budget; university funding; Vietnam War; World War II
- Geduld, HarryJanuary 23, 1996, 96-001; 25 pp.; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 78 minutes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Born on March 3, 1931 in London, England, Harry Maurice Gould served as faculty member in the Engish Department and Comparative Literature Department. Harry discusses his family background, his experiences as a Fulbright Scholar at IU and as in instructor starting in 1962. Additionally, he discusses the development of Film Studies courses on campus and his tenure as Chair of the Department of Comparative Literature from 1990-1996.
  London University; Sheffield University; University of Maryland; University of California at Santa Barbara
  London, England
  English professor
  Barber, Cesar; Calinescu, Matei; Gottesman, Ronald; Naremore, James; Rabkin, Gerald; Weisstein, Ulrcih; Work, James
  English literature; film studies; Fulbright program
- Gentile, Arthur February 15, 1994, 91-235; 17 pages; 1 audiocassette, 45 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Arthur Gentile is a botanist who ended up being a professor and administrator at Indiana University-Kokomo, where he served as vice-chancellor and acting chancellor. He discusses the future of Indiana University-Kokomo, financial problems and concerns, teaching versus research, and important qualities of a university president.
  Indiana University Kokomo; Indiana University Kokomo School of Business; University of Michigan
  academic affairs dean; acting university chancellor; American Institute of Biological Sciences director; university vice-chancellor
  botany; degree programs; Indiana University regional campuses; nursing; teaching vs. research debate; university funding
- Gerrard, CharlotteJune 25, 1996, 96-019; 24 pp.; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips; 73 minutes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Dr. Charlotte Gerrard was born in Stamford, CT on March 10, 1928. In 1965 she was hired as a French professor and continued in the position until her retirement. She discusses cultural changes she obserrved in her time at the university, her teaching philsophosies and research areas, and the development of the Strasbourg study abroad program. Further she discusses the community that developed among faculty in the department and her high and low moments teaching.
  Carnegie Mellon University; Ohio State University; Phi Betta Kappa; University of Pittsburgh; Western College for Women
  New York, New York; Stamford, Connecticut; Strasbourg, France
  French professor; teacher
  Berkvam, Michael; Billant, Antoinette; Carr, Diana; Hope, Quentin; Michael, Keith; Pfohl, Russell; Will, Samuel
  female professors; French Literature; grading practices; literature; research; study abroad
- Getz, George F., Jr. June 5, 1992, 91-108; 7 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 20 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  George Getz, born on January 4, 1908, discusses his involvement with the Arthur R. Metz Foundation which led to a place on the Indiana University Foundation Board. He speaks of how Herman B Wells and Bill Armstrong urged him to participate in the Indiana University Foundation, and tells of some of the general changes the foundation has undergone since he first became active on the board in 1964.
  Arthur R. Metz Foundation; Indiana University Foundation Board
  Armstrong, William; Metz, Arthur R.
- Gibbons, Helen E. November 13, 1996, 96-030; Not transcribed; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 85 minutes; Kraemer, Peter
  Helen Gibbons, born 1929, was a business education professor at IU and IUPU-FW from 1957 until her retirement in 1981. She speaks about her education and interest in business before become a faculty member. She enjoyed observing and helping the student teachers, and discusses teaching methods, students, and other aspects of her career both in Bloomington and Fort Wayne.
  Indiana State University; Indiana University-Purdue University Fort Wayne; Indiana University School of Business
  business professor
  Bloomington, Indiana; Fort Wayne, Indiana
  administrator qualities; business education; female faculty; shorthand; student teachers; teaching methods
- Gilliatt, Neal October 7, 1993, 91-204; 13 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 43 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on December 24, 1917, Neal Gilliatt is a 1939 Indiana University alumnus. In this interview, he discusses his memories of the university from his student days. He speaks of how the Great Depression and World War II affected Indiana University. In addition, he recalls student life at the university in the late nineteen thirties and the changes the campus has since undergone. Gilliatt also relates his memories of Herman B Wells, William Lowe Bryan, and Alfred Kinsey. Finally, Gilliatt, a member of the Indiana University Foundation Board beginning in 1972, discusses the function of the foundation and the need for funding to support continued excellence at Indiana University.
  Indiana University Foundation Board; Kinsey Institute for Research in Sex, Gender, and Reproduction
  Bryan, William Lowe; Kinsey, Alfred C.; Wells, Herman B
  campus development; Great Depression; student life; university funding; university growth; World War II
- Gilman, Alan B. March 16, 1996, 96-012; 36 pages; 1 tape; index, 1 VHS; Carmony, Donald
  Alan B. Gilman attended Indiana University at South Bend from 1948 to 1950, earned his undergraduate degree in history from Indiana University at Bloomington in 1952, and received his MBA from the Indiana University School of Business in 1954. In this interview, Gilman discusses his years growing up in South Bend, Indiana, his years as an undergraduate at Indiana University at South Bend, and charismatic teachers he had at that institution, including Rosemary Daugherty and Dee Perguson. In addition, he discusses Indiana University regional campuses, nontraditional students, and his time at Indiana University at Bloomington. After college, Gilman went on to a long and unusually successful career in business, which began when the Lazarus chain recruited him right after the completion of his last degree.
  General Electric Company; Indiana University Foundation; Indiana University South Bend; IUPUI; Lazarus Department Store; Studebaker Corporation
  Benns, Frank Lee; Buley, Roscoe Carlyle; Daugherty, Rosemary; Lundin, C. Leonard; Perguson, Dee
  Indiana University regional campuses; Indiana University South Bend history; nontraditional students
- Gilman, Alan B. March 26, 1992, 91-089; 15 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 51 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1903, Alan B. Gilman was a 1952 alumnus of Indiana University who also earned his M.B.A. from the Indiana University School of Business in 1954. He speaks of his years as a student and his memories of Indiana University. After being recruited by Lazarus upon graduation, Gilman embarked on a long and successful career as a businessman. He discusses the changes Indiana University has undergone through the years and his continuing involvement with the Indiana University Foundation Board and the dean's advisory committee. In addition, Gilman speaks of his association with F. Lee Benz, John Mee, Bill Armstrong, and Herman B Wells.
  Beta Gamma Sigma; dean's advisory committee; Indiana University Foundation Board; Lazarus Department Store; Phi Beta Kappa
  Armstrong, William; Benns, Frank Lee; Mee, John; Wells, Herman B
  campus development; dean's advisory committee; Indiana University regional campuses; student life; student recruitment
- Glaubinger, Lawrence November 20, 1993, 91-222; 11 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 25 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Lawrence Glaubinger received his BA from Indiana University in 1949, after serving in World War II. He went back to school more than twenty-five years later to receive his business degree. He maintained his connection to Indiana University, serving as an Indiana University Foundation Board member. Glaubinger discusses the changes that have taken place at Indiana University, Herman B Wells, and what he believes the university's mission should be.
  Hoosier 100
  chairperson; Indiana University Foundation Board member; textile converting business person
  1944 GI Bill
- Gonso, Harry April 23, 1992, 91-096; 20 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 56 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean